Guide to the Benjamin Pogrund Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Benjamin Pogrund papers
1925-1996
MS 1261
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14.25
The papers include correspondence, writings, subject files, scrapbooks, clippings, legal documents, photographs, and other materials created and compiled by Benjamin Pogrund, the South African journalist. The collection extensively documents prison conditions in South Africa, the South African Communist Party, the Rand Daily Mail, the South African Coloured National Convention, the South African press, and many other organizations and individuals who worked to subvert apartheid. Featured individuals include Robert Sobukwe, Laurence Gandar, Raymond Louw, John Rees, and Norma Kitson; featured organizations include South African Coloured People's Congress, Pan Africanist Congress, South African Institute of Race Relations, Congress Alliance, and Search for Alternatives.
Pogrund, Benjamin, 1933-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator, 1997.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1961-1996. II. Prisons Files, 1925-1984. III. Subject files, 1939-1995. IV. Writings, 1957-1994. V. Photographs, 1961-1994.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of Benjamin Pogrund, best known for his work as African affairs reporter, night editor, and deputy editor of the Rand Daily Mail. The collection includes Pogrund's correspondence, most notably with the activist Robert Sobukwe while Sobukwe was a political prisoner. Pogrund's writings also comprise a significant portion of the papers, particularly his extensive notes for an unfinished book on the Communist Party in South Africa from 1945 to 1960. Files documenting the Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case," as well as prison conditions in South Africa under apartheid, comprise another important series in the collection. Finally, the papers include a large amount of collected materials regarding various groups and individuals who organized resistance to the South African government while under the apartheid system.
Biographical / Historical
Benjamin Pogrund was born in Cape Town, South Africa on May 5, 1933. He obtained degrees of Bachelor of Arts, Master of Arts, and Bachelor of Social Science at the University of Cape Town between 1950 and 1956 and of Bachelor of Arts in African Studies at Witwatersrand University in 1971.From 1958 to 1985, Pogrund worked in a variety of capacities for the Rand Daily Mail, including African affairs reporter, night editor, and deputy editor. He achieved acclaim and notoriety for his reports on prison conditions and for his coverage of black South African individuals and groups who organized resistance to apartheid. Pogrund also wrote on South African affairs for many publications abroad, including the Boston Globe,Economist,Today,New Republic, and Sunday Times(London) and published several books, including a biography of Robert Sobukwe. Pogrund collected extensive materials documenting the struggle against apartheid and donated them to research libraries around the world. He moved to London in the mid-1980s, where he worked in the foreign departments of several newspapers and commented widely on South Africa. He lived for a short while in the United States during the 1990s before moving to Israel to establish the Center for Social Concern in 1997.
An author, journalist, and editor, Pogrund worked for the Rand Daily Mail in Johannesburg from 1958 to 1985, when the newspaper was shut down due to financial trouble and government pressure. Under the leadership of Laurence Gandar, Raymond Louw, and Pogrund, the Rand Daily Mail became internationally renowned for its coverage of the unjust system of apartheid. Pogrund served in a variety of capacities including African affairs reporter, night editor and deputy editor. While a beat writer on African affairs, Pogrund wrote groundbreaking articles investigating the conditions in which black South Africans lived under apartheid, reporting on the unjust imprisonment of black activists, and giving attention to black politics. He covered the activities of black groups such as the African National Congress and the Pan Africanist Congress and activists such as Nelson Mandela and Robert Sobukwe.
Pogrund was imprisoned and prosecuted twice for his reporting. He was arrested in 1961 and spent eight days in jail for refusing to divulge a source that had given him inside information on government protests conducted on Republic Day of that year. In 1965, Pogrund wrote a series of articles exposing the miserable conditions in South African prisons. The government responded by prosecuting Pogrund, his informants, Laurence Gandar, and the newspaper. The trial became known as the "Prisons Case" and became a showcase for censorship of the press by the South African government. Initially found guilty, the verdict against Pogrund was overturned on appeal in 1972.
Pogrund also wrote on South African affairs for a number of sources outside of South Africa, including the Boston Globe, Economist, Today, New Republic, and Sunday Times (London). Pogrund published several books, including How Can Man Die Better: The Life of Robert Sobukwe.
Through contacts made while investigating and writing about black affairs, Pogrund also acquired a large amount of historical materials documenting the struggle by Africans to end apartheid. Funded first by the Hoover Institution and then the Center for Research Libraries, Pogrund collected and contributed greatly to the microfilm and archival holdings on South African affairs in many U.S. libraries.
After the Rand Daily Mail ceased publication, Pogrund moved to England where he worked in the foreign departments of several newspapers, including the Independent. He spent some time living in the United States in the 1990s before moving to Israel in 1997 to start up the Center for Social Concern, an organization established to facilitate the peace process in the Middle East.
Rand daily mail; Apartheid -- South Africa; Communism -- South Africa; Journalism -- South Africa; Political crimes and offenses -- South Africa; Prisons -- South Africa; Gandar, Laurence; Kitson, Norma; Louw, Raymond, 1926-; Pogrund, Benjamin, 1933-; Rees, J. C. (John Collwyn); Sobukwe, Robert Mangaliso, 1924-1978; Sobukwe, Veronica; Strachan, Harold; Stuart, Kelsey William; Allied Publishers Limited; Pan Africanist Congress; Search for Alternatives; South African Coloured People's Congress; South African Communist Party; South African Institute of Race Relations; South African Coloured National Convention
- Correspondence, 1961-1996, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, Correspondence documents Pogrund's relationships with political activists, journalists, friends, family, and other associates. Letters between Pogrund and noted activist and dissident Robert Sobukwe comprise a particularly important part of the collection. Written predominantly while Sobukwe was imprisoned on Robben Island for organizing a mass protest in 1960, the letters concern a variety of topics, including international affairs, social and political philosophy, religion, and the day to day lives of each man. The Sobukwe correspondence also contains letters between Pogrund and other supporters of Sobukwe, such as Eulalie Stott and Peter Hjul, documenting the extensive efforts to provide Sobukwe with legal representation, food, clothing, books, and other items. Photostats of letters from Sobukwe to his wife Veronica, letters from other members of Sobukwe's family to Pogrund, and one folder of speeches are also listed under Robert Sobukwe.
  Correspondence between Pogrund and Rand Daily Mail colleagues Laurence O. V. Gandar, Raymond Louw, and Harold Strachan comprises another portion of the series. The letters document the affairs of the newspaper, particularly the Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case." Additional material on the "Prisons Case" and the Rand Daily News generally can be found in Series II and III respectively.
  The series also includes a small amount of personal correspondence. Two folders of letters from Norma Kitson to Pogrund and one folder of correspondence with Astrid Pogrund document his romantic relationships.
  Four folders of general correspondence, arranged chronologically, are listed at the beginning of the series.
  - General, 1962-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Bell, Dewer and Hall [attorneys], 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bennett, George, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Carter, Gwendolen, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Economist, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    General
    See also: Series IV, folders 80-81
  - Fleischer, Anthony, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gandar, Laurence O. V., 1965, 1988-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    See also: Oversize, folder 7
    General note
    See also: Series II, folders 45-48
  - Hirson, Baruch, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hjul, Peter, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    See also: Series I, folders 36-44
  - Hoover Institution, Stanford University, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Joffe, Joel, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Karis, Thomas
    See also: Series III, folder 38
    See also: Series III, folder 68
  - Kathrada, A. M., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kitson, Norma, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Lekota, Cynthia, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lekota, Patrick, 1985, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lollam, Stanley, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Louw, Raymond, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    See also: Series III, folder 15
    See also: Series III, folder 55
  - Malie, Julius, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Maloney, Pat, 1964, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Mandela, Winnie, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Postcard of Winnie Mandela was reported missing in 2018.
  - Mathopeng, Zephaniah, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Matthews, Z. K., 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mbeki, Govan, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ngwenya, Thomas, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Ntloedibe, Elias L., 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pogrund, Astrid, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rees, John C., 1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    See also: Series III, folders 62-67
  - Republic of South Africa. Ministry of Justice [requests for permission to possess Communist literature], 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Sacks, Andrew, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Sobukwe, Robert
    - Pogrund, Benjamin, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 36-44)
    - Sobukwe family [correspondence with Benjamin Pogrund], 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Sobukwe, Veronica [photostats of letters from Robert Sobukwe], 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 46-47)
    - Speeches by Robert Sobukwe, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Writings about Robert Sobukwe (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Sobukwe, Veronica [correspondence with Robert Sobukwe], 1962-1967, 1975, 1989-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
    See also: Series IV, folder 78
  - Stott, Eulalie
  - Strachan, Harold, 1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    See also: Series II, folder 33
    See also: Series II, folders 42-44
  - Strachan, Maggie, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Tobias, Phillip V., 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Tristam, Hugh, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Zug, James [re: New Age], 1994 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Prisons Files, 1925-1984, undated
  Prisons Files consist of a wide variety of materials Pogrund created and collected while writing about and working to transform the penal system in South Africa. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and most of the series falls under three headings: Legal proceedings, Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case," and Statements by prisoners.
  Legal proceedings document court cases between prisoners and specific prisons or the South African government. The files predominantly contain transcripts of proceedings, but they also include some correspondence, clippings, notes, and other materials relating to specific cases.
  In 1965, the Rand Daily Mail ran a series of exposés on the conditions for prisoners incarcerated in the Republic of South Africa. The government charged that the reports were false and took the newspaper to court. Pogrund, Laurence Gandar, Raymond Louw, and Harold Strachan were named specifically in the charges and the subsequent court case became a major news story and an obvious source of tension between the media and the South African government. The files that pertain to the case include the Pogrund articles on prison conditions, clippings, correspondence, court transcripts, legal documents, and other miscellaneous materials. Pogrund also kept several scrapbooks of clippings that cover the events surrounding the case that are listed with the Oversize materials. Other files on the Rand Daily Mail can be found in Series III and more of Pogrund's writings on the trials and prison conditions in general can be found in the newspaper articles section of Series IV.
  Statements by prisoners consist of interviews Pogrund and others conducted and compiled in support of their research on prison conditions. The stories told in the statements document the miserable conditions many prisoners in South African jails endured while being detained. Andrew Sacks, Isaac Setsheti, Harold Strachan, Filisberto Taimo, and Johannes Adries Theron are some of the individuals whose prison experiences are covered in these files.
  Files under "Republic Day Protest" pertain to Pogrund's imprisonment for failing to disclose his sources for a story he ran about demonstrations carried out on Republic Day in 1961. The series also includes a select number of topical files on electric shock treatment, the farm labor system, the Police Act of 1979, the Republic of South Africa's Department of Prisons, typhoid, and the United Nations Commission on Human Rights.
  - General [clippings about prisons], 1925-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Electric shock treatment, 1965-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Farm labor system, 1959-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Improvement in prison conditions, 1965-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Johannesburg prison, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Legal proceedings
    - Goldberg, Denis Theodore, and eight others vs. Minister of Prisons, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
    - Harris, Frederick John vs. Commissioner of Prisons, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
    - Hassim, Nina and Kadir vs. Robben Island Prison, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 15-19)
    - Regina vs. multiple parties, 1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Scholes, John, undated (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
      See also: Series V, folder 14
    - Van Schalwyck, Gysbert Johan
      - Interviews and statements, [1965] (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
      - Transcripts of proceedings, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
  - Police Act, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - "Prison Conditions in South Africa: A Factual Report" [compiled by Amnesty International], 1965 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case"
    - Articles
      - Pogrund, Benjamin, [1965] (Box 6, Folder 29-32)
      - Strachan, Harold, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Background materials, 1960-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 34-40)
    - Clippings, 1967-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Comparison of charges with State vs. Strachan and State vs. Theron, ca. 1965 (Box 7, Folder 42-44)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 45-48)
    - Court transcripts, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Legal documents, statements, and memoranda, 1965-[1969] (Box 8, Folder 50-53)
    - Letters of support, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 54)
      See also: Series V, folders 9-12
    - Pogrund vs. Dr. Percy Yutar, 1966-1968, undated (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Pogrund's appeal
      - Court documents, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 9, Folder 57)
      See also: Oversize, folders 3-6
  - Republic Day Protest [Pogrund's imprisonment]
    - General, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Clippings, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Republic of South Africa Department of Prisons
    - General, 1960-1969, undated (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Prisoner's handbook, ca. 1964 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Statements by prisoners
    - Joffe, Joel
      Series I, folder 16
    - Sacks, Andrew, 1966, undated (Box 9, Folder 62-63)
      Series V, box 33, folder 13
    - Setsheti, Isaac, 1967, undated (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Strachan, Harold, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - Taimo, Filisberto, 1965, undated (Box 9, Folder 66)
      Series V, box 33, folder 16
    - Theron, Johannes Adries, 1965-1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1969, 1984, undated (Box 10, Folder 68-75)
  - Study questionnaire, undated (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Typhoid epidemic, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - United Nations, Report of the Commission on Human Rights [re: South African prisons], 1968 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Victor Verster Prison Complex, undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
- Subject Files, 1939-1995, undated
  Subject Files document a wide variety of individuals, organizations, countries, and topics relating to Pogrund's multi-faceted professional and political interests. The files are arranged alphabetically and most are comprised of materials Pogrund collected in the course of his activities.
  The series includes many files documenting specific political groups that opposed the apartheid system in South Africa, such as the Congress Alliance, the Pan Africanist Congress, the Congress of Democrats, the South African Council on Trade Unions, the South African Coloured People's Congress, the African National Congress, the Black Sash, the Liberal Party of South Africa, the Ninety Day Protest Committee, the South African Communist Party, and the Union Council of Coloured Affairs. Collected publications, pamphlets, and other items comprise a substantial amount of materials documenting the efforts of the South African Institute of Race Relations. The series also holds a substantial amount of material regarding the South African Coloured National Convention of 1961. Folders relating to Search for Alternatives contain information on Pogrund's efforts with John Rees to find a functional alternative to the rule of apartheid.
  Along with several files listed under South African Press, the series includes folders on the media in South Africa and the rest of the world. Most significant among these are materials covering "Challenging the Censors: World News Media Action Conference," the Newspaper Press Union of South Africa, the South African Press Council, the South African Society of Journalists, and the World Press Freedom Committee. Files relating to the Rand Daily Mail document the operation of the newspaper and its closing in 1985. Researchers should consult Series II for materials about the Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case." Programs created by Pogrund and others to train Africans to become reporters are listed under "Black journalist training."
  Subject Files also contains several folders pertaining to formal government "Commissions of Inquiry" into Alleged Irregularities in the Former Department of Information; the Mass Media; and the Riots in Soweto.
  Pogrund's efforts to collect historical information to be placed into libraries and other cultural institutions are filed under Center for Research Libraries, Public libraries, and Research libraries. Correspondence with the Hoover Institute in Series I also documents these efforts.
  Collections of materials Pogrund compiled about specific individuals (Stephen Biko, Ruth Hayman, John Horak, Clements Kodali, Nelson Mandela, Andrew Silk, Rosemary Wentzel) and countries (Lesotho, Mozambique, Namibia) round out the remainder of the series.
  - African National Congress, 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - African People's Democratic Union of Southern Africa [Draft Constitution], undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Bantu education, 1948-1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Biko, Stephen, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Black journalist training, 1980-1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Black Sash, 1967, 1981-1985 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Center for Research Libraries [re: microfilming project], 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  - Challenging the Censors: World News Media Action Conference, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Commission of Inquiry into Alleged Irregularities in the Former Department of Information [Erasmus Commission]
    - General, 1977, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Report on Department of Information, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Mass Media [Steyn Commission]
    - General, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Memorandum submitted by the South African Society of Journalists, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Commission of Inquiry into the Riots in Soweto [Cillie], 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Congress Alliance
    - All-in-Africa Conference, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Joint National Executives, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - National Consultative Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Pamphlets, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Reports, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Stay at home demonstration, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Congress of Democrats, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Defense Aid Fund, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Federation of Free African Trade Unions, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Ford Motor Company [re: disinvestment alternative], 1987 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Hayman, Ruth, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Horak, John, 1992, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Human Rights Welfare Committee, Banished People
    - General, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Clippings, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Reports, 1958-1961 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Wine festival
      Oversize, folder 8
  - Johannesburg Bantu Revenue Account, undated (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Kadali, Clements ["I See You Whiteman!," book manuscript], undated (Box 13, Folder 33-35)
  - Lesotho, 1984, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Liberal Party of South Africa, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Mandela, Nelson [re: Central Intelligence Agency involvement in his, 1962, 1990-1994, undated (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Mozambique, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Nambia, 1977-1981 (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - National Liberation League of South Africa, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Newspaper Press Union of South Africa, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Ninety-day Protest Committee, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Non-European United Front of South Africa [draft constitution], undated (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Pan Africanist Congress, 1961-1965, undated (Box 13, Folder 45-46)
  - Pageview Standholders and Trading Association, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - Persian Gulf War [re: press censorship], 1991 (Box 13, Folder 48)
  - Prestel Viewdata System, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 49)
  - Public libraries, 1963-1964 (Box 13, Folder 50)
  - Rand Daily Mail
    - General, 1977-1994 (Box 14, Folder 51-53)
    - Clippings, 1958-1985 (Box 14, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 55)
    - Financial report, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 56-57)
    - Research notes, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 58)
  - Research libraries, 1961-1963 (Box 15, Folder 59-60)
  - Roodepoort-Maraisburg Rotary Club Symposia on South Africa, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 61)
  - Search for Alternatives, 1977-1981, undated (Box 15, Folder 62-67)
    Series I, folder 33
  - Silk, Andrew [writings about Robert Sobukwe], 1978-1995, undated (Box 15, Folder 68)
  - South African Coloured People's Congress, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 69)
  - South African Coloured National Convention
    - General, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 70)
    - Clippings, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 71)
    - Continuation committee, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 73)
    - Executive committee, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 74)
    - Planning committee, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 75)
    - Proceedings, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 76)